<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The foundation and rise of many of the practices, customs, and formallities of the priests, lawyers, and people of England examined, and found to be from the pope and his authority in some queries to the priests, lawyers, and professors, for any of them to answer : in order to the purging of themselves (if they can) from being truly adjudged the practisers and upholders of the Popes superstitions innovations, institutions, and imposings, since the time (and against the practises) of the Apostles, and pure primitive church / by a member of the true Church that is in God, in whose name and behalf this is printed, by me, Thomas Hart.</title>
            <author>Hart, Thomas, 1629-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10271</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12198874</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12198874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 763:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The foundation and rise of many of the practices, customs, and formallities of the priests, lawyers, and people of England examined, and found to be from the pope and his authority in some queries to the priests, lawyers, and professors, for any of them to answer : in order to the purging of themselves (if they can) from being truly adjudged the practisers and upholders of the Popes superstitions innovations, institutions, and imposings, since the time (and against the practises) of the Apostles, and pure primitive church / by a member of the true Church that is in God, in whose name and behalf this is printed, by me, Thomas Hart.</title>
                  <author>Hart, Thomas, 1629-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FOUNDATION AND Riſe of many of the Practiſes, Cuſtoms, and Formallities of the <hi>Prieſts, Lawy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England</hi> Examined, and found to be from the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Authority.</p>
            <p>IN SOME QUERIES TO THE <hi>Prieſts, Lawyers,</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> for any of them to ANSVVER; In Order to the Purging of themſelves (if they can) from being truly adjudged the Practiſers and Upholders of the <hi>Popes</hi> Superſtitions, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, Inſtitutions, and Impoſings, ſince the time (and againſt the Practiſes) of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and pure Primitive Church.</p>
            <p>By a Member of the true Church that is in God, in whoſe Name and behalf this is Printed, By me <hi>Thomas Hart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:56052:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56052:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO ALL THE <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> and <hi>Lawyers</hi> IN ENGLAND: Anſwer us theſe <hi>Queries</hi> in Writing, or Print.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether or no you are not Levened with the old way of Popery? And whether or no you have not the old Leven of Popery amongſt you ſecretly in your hearts, and under your skirts and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Come to plainneſs without any evaſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 2. Do not you call all your Courts in the Names of the Dayes given from the Pope, and your Terms, as <hi>Hillary Term, Eaſter Term, Trinity Term, Michaelmas Term?</hi> And do not you require all men to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in your Courts, by the Names of your Saint Dayes, as eight dayes after St. <hi>Hillary,</hi> fifteen dayes after St. <hi>Hillary,</hi> eight dayes after the <hi>Purification,</hi> and at ſo many dayes after <hi>Eaſter,</hi> the morrow of the <hi>Aſcention day,</hi> the morrow of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56052:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Trinity,</hi> and ſo many dayes after <hi>Trinity,</hi> and ſo many dayes after St. <hi>Michael,</hi> the morrow of <hi>All Souls,</hi> the morrow of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> and the like? And are not all theſe Reliques of Popery, lodging in your boſome, and ſhewing you have not the with nor wiſdom, ye Lawyers, and Judges, and Prieſts, and Teachers beyond the papiſts and Pope, to call your people to your Courts but in the Names of the dayes that the Pope has given, now how are ye in the ſupream above the Pope, how do you deny the Pope here, and renounce Popery here, or how do you renounce his ſupream power when theſe things are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you in your Authority, in your Courts; Now if you ſay ye cannot, or know not how to call your people to your Courts in any other Name than the Pope has given to the dayes, then he is your School Maſter, then he is your Teacher, and you have not found another Teacher yet, then the Pope is head yet, to teach you, of Prieſts, Lawyers, and Judges, to teach you to give Names to your dayes, by which ye know the dayes, and the people come to know that they muſt Anſwer on them at your Courts; now if you ſay this is not Popery, the naming of theſe dayes by the Saints names, and appearing ſuch a Saint day, and calling your Terms and Courts by ſuch dayes, and then people to anſwer at the Term after ſuch a Saint day; of whom learned you it but of the Pope? And was not he the Author of it, did Chriſt or his Apoſtles teach you ſuch a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or are you taught out of the Scriptures ſuch a Doctrine? Now if you have not the wiſdom to give Names to your days, Lawyers, Teachers, and Judges, and Magiſtrates without the Popes help, but be fain to call your dayes by the ſame names as the Pope gave, how do not you feel his Superſtitions amongſt you, does not his power ſtand up, how is his Image ſlain, are not thoſe his Marks amongſt you of his Leven; were theſe Names of Saints amongſt the Apoſtles before their deceaſe, or come up ſince their deceaſe? Come, if you will have Popery renounced amongſt you root and branch, and reliques, and the leven, and his marks, and his image, and his power, and his authority, root out all that he ſet up, root it out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 3. Who gave Names to all your Steeple-houſes, and called them Churches? Were they not Papiſts Houſes, and their Names given to them by the Pope, and his authority, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56052:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>power, as St. <hi>Maries,</hi> St. <hi>Peters,</hi> St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> and were theſe Steeple-houſes ever St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> St. <hi>Peters,</hi> St. <hi>Maries,</hi> St. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garats, &amp;c.</hi> Now has not the Popes power a high degree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you yet, and has the Prieſts, Lawyers, Judges, ever yet manifeſted a wiſdom, an underſtanding or knowledge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Popes, to teach the people, not to call their houſes by the Popes Names that he has given to them, and not to call the dayes by the Popes Names that he has given to them, as Saints dayes, St. <hi>Luke,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> St. <hi>Mark,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> and <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide;</hi> where did ever any of the Apoſtles or Saints before their diſceaſe name their dayes after this manner, or teach the people to do ſo, or Chriſt either; but what has been ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles in the Apoſtacy, and how are you come out of the Apoſtacy, or to deny the Popes teachings, though you may do it in words outwardly, yet its his wiſdom and knowledge, that has given Names to your dayes, and to your Churches as you call them, which are made uſe of by you, and not anothers, as is plainly declared by your fruits on the houſe top; Now how can you ſay you are not Popiſhly affected, when all theſe Dreggs are amongſt you, lyes in the Barrel unpurged out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querié</hi> 4. Are not all your Acts and Lawes given forth and made in the Name of ſuch a day, as <hi>Munday,</hi> and <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> and <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> and <hi>Thurſday,</hi> and <hi>Friday,</hi> and <hi>Satterday;</hi> And ſuch a Month, as <hi>January,</hi> and <hi>February,</hi> and <hi>March,</hi> and <hi>April,</hi> and <hi>May,</hi> and <hi>June,</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt;</hi> has not all theſe things been learned of the Heathen and Papiſts: the Papiſts who apoſtated from the truth, and the Heathen who worſhiped the Sun and Moon and Stars, and ſhew that they have been your teachers, their wiſdom has taught you to name your Dayes, and your Months, and that you have not a wiſdom beyond their wiſdom to teach the people the contrary, and does not this ſhew that you are apoſtated from the true Chriſtians, and the true Jewes, who called the Dayes, the <hi>Firſt day,</hi> and <hi>Second day,</hi> and <hi>Third day,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Seventh day:</hi> and <hi>Firſt month, Second month, Third month,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Twelfth month:</hi> And are not you that call your Months by the Names that the Heathen gave, and call your Dayes by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56052:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Names of Saints, that the papiſts gave them, and by the names that the Heathen gave them, as <hi>Suns day,</hi> and <hi>Moons day,</hi> that worſhiped the <hi>Sun,</hi> and called it the <hi>Suns day,</hi> that worſhiped the <hi>Moon</hi> and called it the <hi>Moons day,</hi> that worſhiped <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> and called it <hi>Saturns day</hi> and the reſt, as your <hi>Almanacks</hi> declare, form'd amongſt the Papiſts and Heathen, is not here Heatheniſm &amp; Popery, and Idolatry, both going together, and Heatheniſm and Popery, and you found amongſt them, and they amongſt you, out of the true Jewes life an language, and of the true Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 5. And has not many of your biggeſt ſort of Bibles called Church Bibles, croſſes in them ſtanding at the verſes ends, ſo full of lying ſigns, and while thoſe are ſtanding how have you blotted out Popery and the Popes image, and mark, and ſign; and how is it that ſo many Croſſes yet ſtand upon the Steeple-houſe ends in many parts of the Nation, and in high Wayes, and Market-places, and pictures in the Windows and Images, if Popery be caſt out and renounced amongſt you: behold all people as ye paſſe up and down, and take notice of all the Steeple-houſes in <hi>England,</hi> and high Wayes, and ſee if there be not upon many of them a Croſs; now how is it you ſay, that you have renounced Popery, and the Popes mark, the Popes image, and the Popes ſign ſtands up upon the houſe top yet, and calling up the people in the Names of the Saints days to Terms and Courts, and calling the names of your Churches by the Saints Names yet, how is the Popes power killed here and his image thrown down, when the Croſs ſtands upon the end of the Steeple-houſe, and the pictures in the Windows, and the Steeple-houſe called by the name of Saints, and the holy Bell, the <hi>Saints Bell</hi> rings, <hi>Ting, ting,</hi> as you may hear up and down in <hi>London</hi> and many places; was not all this done by the Popes teaching and the Popes wiſdom, and the popes power, which he calls ſupream, and your Prieſts yet ſtanding up in them and not crying againſt them, how have you here renounced Popery?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 6. Was not all your ſprinkling Infants from the Pope? Did it not firſt riſe from him? Was not all your tythes, temples, ſteeple-houſes, chappels firſt ſet up by the Pope, and by him called Churches, there is a Croſs on the end of them,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56052:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>which is a ſign who ſet them up, not yet thrown down; is not this a ſign of abundance of Idolatry, and Popery, and Popiſh affection that is amongſt people of the Nation yet, while Tythes, and Temple, and Pulpit, and Prieſts, and Croſſes, St. <hi>Peters,</hi> St. <hi>Maries,</hi> St. <hi>Pauls</hi> houſes ſtands up and calling peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to appear ſuch a day by ſuch a Saints Name, is not all this ſet up by Pope and Papiſts? And has not Popery a great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity while theſe things are ſtanding, and his Name great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt people, and his image not ſpoiled? And have not you his mark in your hand, while you have your Names to your dayes as he gave, and your Names to your Churches as he gave, and the Croſs on the end of your Churches which he ſet up, and do not you call them by the ſame Name that he gave both your Dayes and your Churches, and ſo how do not you here ſtand in the Popes power, how do you renounce it, when you have his image, his mark, his names yet amongſt you? Are not theſe the Popes images, marks, and names, Saints dayes, holy dayes, which ye gave forth your Summons to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> ſuch a Saints day, and call your Houſes by the Names that the Pope gave, and Croſſes, are not theſe his Marks and Images, which are not yet down and ſpoyl'd?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 7. From whence came all your Pariſhes, and who was the ſetter of them up, and the builders of your Steeple-houſes, and ſetting them Eaſt and Weſt, and ſetting the Porches and Chancels, and the Body of the Houſe, what was the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, the Temple and <hi>Jewes</hi> Synagogues, and who was the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitator of all this, if not the Pope, and done by his power, and Hallowed, and Conſecrated by it, and ſo do not they call it Holy Ground ever ſince, and ſo is not that the place where neither Prieſt nor Curate might or may be ſpoke to, though one be moved of the Lord, without impriſonment, and has it not been the Pope and his power that has quenched the Spirit?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 8. And how came up all your Churching of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and who has had the Marrying of people, and from whence had the Prieſts that power, if not from the Pope at the firſt, for does not their Prieſts Marry, and is not all your Tythes, Pulpits, Temples, Prieſts, ſet up by the Popes power and authority, which have the pictures, the croſſes at the end of them, and has not all theſe been ſet up ſince the daye, of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56052:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Apoſtles in the Apoſtacy, and all to be judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the Popes power, with the Popes authority?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 9. And is not all your making Miniſters by the will of man by Schools and Colledges, as ye pretend for Chriſt, as the Papiſts makes them by Schools and Colledges, and did not the Pope ſet up your Colledges and gave them their names, of <hi>Chriſts Colledge,</hi> St <hi>Johns Colledge, Trinity Colledge, Imanuel Colledge, Jesus Colledge, All Souls Colledge, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen dalen Colledge, &amp;c.</hi> And have not you been beholden to the Pope for his wiſdom, and has not he been your Teacher in all theſe things, and when did you renounce his Doctrine and his Teaching in all theſe things, and throw it out of the Nation, and does not his Doctrine ſtand here amongſt you for a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial, and was not all this Teaching from him that gave your Names to your Colledges, to your Steeple-houſes, to your Dayes, and is not the ſtink of Popery amongſt you while all theſe Names and Images are ſo frequent amongſt you, ſpoke up and down your ſtreets, and how can the Papiſts and Jeſuits but laugh at you when ye deny them in words, yet embrace their Doctrine, Practice, and Superſtitions, was not this the Popes Doctrine to give theſe Names to your Houſes and Colledges, as St. <hi>Peters, Trinities, Johns, Pauls,</hi> and as yet calling your Dayes by the Saints Names, if you ſay nay, then declare by Scripture where the Apoſtles gave any ſuch Names to Dayes, ſet up Colledges, gave any ſuch Names to them, as <hi>Trinity, Peters, Johns,</hi> or ſet up any such Houſes with Bells in them, and a Pulpit, and a Glaſs, does not the Papiſts ſay their Maſs by the Hour-glaſs? Do not you read your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons written in your Papers by the Glaſſe, or ſpeak what you can remember of the Scriptures, or the old Fathers Expoſition of them by the Glaſſe, and does not this favour of Popery, and now how can you take to Oath of Abjuration amongſt you to ſwear againſt all Popery, and ſwear to deny all Popery, and Croſſes ſtands upon your Steeple-houſes ends, the Popiſh-houſe ends, and you call your Steeple-houſes by popiſh names given to them, and you call your Colledges by Popiſh names, and you call your Dayes by Popiſh names, your Months and Week-dayes by Popiſh and Heathen names, which ſhews the Popes Doctrine is not denyed, and here is the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56052:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Popes Leven amongſt e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, which I ſay to all people beware of it, which has got up ſince the dayes of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 10. And have you not had all your degrees, orders, as Bachelers of Arts, Maſters of Arts, Batchelers of Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Doctors of Divinity, Doctors of Phyſick, Doctors of Laws; was not the Pope the firſt letter up of this, and the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower and giver of the Maintenance to maintain this by his power, and then gave to the Colledges the names of the Saints. Now come and ſee all if you can ſtand on your own Leggs, without the Popes Doctrine, without the <hi>Popes</hi> Orders, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Popes</hi> Teaching, without the <hi>Popes</hi> Wiſdom, without the <hi>Popes</hi> Inſtructions, and if you can give Names to your Houſes without the <hi>Popes</hi> counſel, give names to your called Churches without the <hi>Popes</hi> counſel, and give names to your Dayes without him; was not he the firſt that called them Churches, and holy Houſes; come let us ſee how you can ſtand now and throw the <hi>Popes</hi> counſel aſide, the <hi>Popes</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the <hi>Popes</hi> wiſdom; come ye that be of your Colledges, and Prieſts, and Lawyers, and Judges; let us ſee how you can name your dayes, and your months, not as the <hi>Pope</hi> and the Heathen do: ſee how you can name them; let us ſee if you have a wiſdom beyond their wiſdom, and how you can have your dayes, and months, and not as the Heathen, not as the <hi>Pope</hi> and his counſel; let us ſee how you can ſtand on your own leggs without the <hi>Popes</hi> help, and Heathens help and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; what are not ye able to give Names to your Dayes, to your Months, to your Colledges, to the Houſes, your Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges by the Names that the Papiſts gave them, and your names as the Heathen did? O what is your ignorance? Were the Apoſtles ſeven years at a School, before they went and preached Chriſt: oh abominable! and were not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts the firſt beginners of this? and was not all this in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy ſince the Apoſtles? and muſt the Spirit be quenched in others that have not ſerved the Apprentiſhip? and is not this like another Trade, that till I have ſerved ſeven years, I may not ſet up, there was a Law to the contrary, and has not this Law been among the Prieſts, that none ſhall ſpeak in their Steeple-houſes, or Pulpits, or ſpeak to them without a priſon?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56052:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and does not all this ſmell and taſte of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Pope;</hi> who had a Law that none ſhould ſpeak to the Pri<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ts, but it was called Diſturbance: as witneſs Queen <hi>Mary</hi> one of the arms of his Tree where he leaſt ſheltred under; and has not all his limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the holy One, quenchi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Sprit, been ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles amongſt the ap<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es from the true Church, who ſaid, if any thing be revealed to another that ſits by, let the firſt hold his peace,; you may all propheſie one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted, for God was not the author of confuſion, but of pence: and this was in all the Churches of the Saints. Now is not this confuſion amongſt you and your Teachers, to bid him hold his tongue, there is ſomething revealed to another that ſits by, and ſhews that all your Church be in the apoſtacy from the Apoſtles Doctrine; and you be all them that be gone from the Spirit, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Saints were in that gave forth the Scripture, but only have the Sheeps cloathing, the outſide, and has not that cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Woolviſh ſpirit in you? has not the Fruits in this. Age declated it? did ever any of the Apoſtles before their deceaſe, or the Churches, make ſuch work amongſt the people for Tythes as you do in your Pariſhes, which is this day one of the greateſt things in the Nation, that you are ſuing, haling the people (before Courts, Juſtices, Benches for Maintenance, whom you are not able to reſiſt in the ſpirit, with all your Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, Learning, who have been ſeven years at your Trade, at yous Schools, that a company of innocent people, which many of them cannot read letters ſhould confound all your wiſdom, which before them is not able to ſtand; wonder and be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and confeſs that the Spirit which gave forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is again made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 11. When Queen <hi>Mary</hi> had ſet up Popery in the Nation; was there not many of the people then in thoſe daies which cryed againſt popery, and cryed againſt the popiſh Prieſts, and went into the popiſh houſes, the Steeple-houſes; then did not ſhe make a Law and a Decree, that whoſoever did diſturb Prieſt or Curate in the Church, or Church-yard, preaching, ſinging, or giving the Maſs, defacing or marring a <hi>Croſs</hi> in the Church, or Church-yard, he ſhould be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned three months; and was not it called maliciouſly, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56052:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>done, that to mar their Croſſes then, and cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Prieſts then; and was not he called a diſturber that would have marred their Croſſes, or broken their Pictures out of the windows, or ſpoke to the prieſt in that they call their Church, or Church-yard? and did not many of them ſuffer impriſonment, and ſome of them Martyrs? and has not the prieſts of our Age been by the ſame Law guarded, that has the popiſh Houſe, and their Church as they call it, and Church-yard, and Croſs on the end of it, and pictures in the windows of it; and if any did ſpeak to the Prieſt in the Popiſh houſe that they call the Church, he was to ſuffer by the ſame Law as a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious diſturber; Now how has our Prieſts here of the Nation renounced Popery when they had their Law to guard them, and cry the others did well in the dayes of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> that cryed againſt popery who ſuffered by the Law; and they do ill now who ſuffer by the ſame Law, becauſe they cry againſt them that are guarded with it, which many of the Martyrs ſuffered by; and they uſed the ſame Weapons againſt ſuch as the Lord God moved to cry againſt them, Popery, and Papiſts, and Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Law, and the popiſh Houſe and Croſs on the end of it, and the Prieſts that uphold it, and the Colledges by which they were made which were named of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the dayes which are named after the Saints, and yet theſe which are covered with popery, their Houſes, their Names, their Maintenance, their Tythes, their Garments ſmell with it, and have been guarded by the Papiſts Law, ſuch as they know cannot ſwear at all, but declare againſt them, and the Papiſts alſso, to ſuch they put the Oath of Abjuration, to ſuch as they know cannot ſwear who are true Chriſtians, out of the apoſtacy in the Doctrine of Chriſt and the Apoſtles before the Papiſts were, who ſet their foot upon all the Papiſts upon the earth, and their Likeneſſes, and Images, and Croſſes, and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes, and all the train of it, head and tail they trample un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot, bred or born; was not the <hi>Pope</hi> the firſt ſetter up that people ſhould teach for handfuls of Barley, and ſhocks of Corn and Peaſe, and Wool, and their Eaſter-Reckonings, and Midſomer dues; was not the <hi>Pope</hi> the firſt ordainer of this? Come Prieſts, and Lawyers, and Judges, how ſmells your Garments of popery in all theſe things? where are your
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56052:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>free Goſpel-teachers, when your Prieſts and Teachers are quarrelling with people for reek-pennies, and plow-peannies, and money for gardens, bees, foals, milk, eggs, hemp and flax, and apples, and plums; now does not all hear your Garments ſtink of popery? was not the <hi>Pope</hi> the firſt riſe of all this, who ravened from the Spirit ſince the Apoſtles? where is your freely-received freely give; is the gift of God to be ſold for money, to be compared, or equalled, or meaſured with earthly things? oh ye are in the gall of bitterneſs; did ever any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt quarrel for out ward things, and caſt people in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to priſon till they dye, as the Prieſts of this Nation do keep peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in priſon becauſe they will not give them maintenance, keep ſome in priſon till they die, oh abominable, make all your Names ſtink through all Nations; are not your Prieſts and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Nation, National Prieſts that puts in priſon thoſe that cannot pay you Tythes, and put in your mouths, and you will keep them in priſon till they die, as ſome of you have done, who have kept in the priſon till they die; are not you here as bad or worſe than the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> for do they in <hi>Spaine</hi> keep any in priſon till they die? do they keep them in priſon becauſe they cannot give them maintenance, or becauſe they cannot bow to their Worſhips? Now you that caſt people in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to priſon becauſe they cannot pay you your Tythes, and will not let them come out till they die, how or wherein do you differ from the Papists Inquiſition; and how, and who was the firſt author of this? did Chriſt ſend you forth to do ſo, and this work; or the Apoſtles give you a command to do ſo? nay you will caſt them in priſon, and put them in priſon, and take trebble damage of them, or three or four times the value, for whom you do no work, and are not Miniſters too; does the Papiſts ſo; and caſt them into priſon till death; what is this but like a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> and the ſmell of popery, and not the ſmell of a Chriſtian; are not you in this from Chriſt, and the Apoſtle apoſtated, nay is it not worſe than a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> for there they are carried before a Court, and have a tryal and judgement; but here the <hi>Prieſts</hi> can ſend to she Lawyers for a Writ, and by that the Magiſtrate Will take their bodies, and put them in priſon, and there keep them without either hearing, trial, or judgement, weeks, months, and years, yea till they die in priſon.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56052:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Querie</hi> 12. Who made the Prieſts and your Miniſters, did not the Biſhops? And who made the Biſhops, did not the Pope and Cardinals? And ſo has not the Pope been the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel that you all came out at in the Apoſtacy; and is not he the Key and the Door you all came through, which all theſe Tyths, Temples, Prieſts, making of Prieſts, Colledges, Names after the Saints to dayes, to your houſes, has run through his Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel and opened with his Key, the <hi>Popes</hi> Key, and ſet up by his authority: Now if you do ſay and argue that the <hi>Pope,</hi> though he was in error, might make Miniſters, and you do ſucceed from the Apoſtles, with whom Chriſt ſaid he would be to the end of the world through him: I ſay no, you cannot ſucceed from the Apoſtles through him, for he being Apoſtated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, ravened from the Spirit of Chriſt, and gone from the Apoſtles, and got the sheeps cloathing, that is the outſide, but inwardly a ravening Wolf, that is ravened over moſt part of Nations; and he having inwardly ravened, gone from the Apoſtles; having got the Sheeps cloathing, Chriſts and the Prophets, and Apoſtles words, the outſide from him, in this you are Succeſſors, as your fruits have declared, who has the outſide as he has the Sheeps cloathing, but inwardly ravening Wolves, ravening up and down for your prey, and would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſuch as cannot put into your mouths, and are contrary minded to you, and give you Maintenance, and give you Tyths, which neither you nor the Pope are the Succeſſors of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles whom he would be with to the end of the world, for ſuch Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, <hi>that if it was poſſible ſhould deceive the very Elect,</hi> in the 7. and 24. of <hi>Matthew;</hi> which <hi>Paul, Peter,</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> ſaw was come and coming, and <hi>John</hi> ſaw al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in the world, and went forth from them, ſo <hi>Mark,</hi> went forth from the Apoſtles, ſo not Succeſſors, ſuch as had the Sheeps cloathing, which all that dwelt upon the earth went after, and all Nations came to drink the cup of Fornicat on; which ſhould make war againſt the Saints, and overcome them, them that kept the teſtimony of Jeſus, the ſpirit of Propheſie, them that ravened from the Spirit, which all the world went after, and them that a welt upon the earth worſhiped, and here came up the firſt Beaſt, and ſecond Beaſt, and all his Names and Heads, and Horns, which all that dweit upon the earth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56052:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>wandered after; and the cry has been; who is able to make war with him; ſo theſe that inwardly reigned, whored, went forth from the Apoſtles with all that dwelt upon the earth, went after, and all Nations drunk the cup of Fornication, the Kings of the earth, theſe preached not the Goſpel, though they had the Sheepsclothing, which were ravened from the life; theſe were the deceivers of the World, and the Nations. And again, the beaſt and falſe prophets ſhould be taken, and the downfal of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the great Whore judged, and the Saints and the Lamb get the victory, and the everlaſting Goſpel come to the preached to them that dwell upon the earth again, for all that dwell upon the earth had worſhipped the beaſt, and drunk the cup of Fornication, the Whores cup, which Chriſt ſaid ſhould come, which inwardly ravened, which has had the Sheeps clothing; theſe has not been the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of the Apoſtles which went forth from them, that is clearly ſeen, which all Nations of the world went after, and drunk their cup; and ſo I challenge you all to anſwer, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt you all to be the <hi>Popes</hi> ſucceſſors, and whether or no you and they be not of the ſtock which Chriſt ſaid ſhould come in wardly ravening, got he Sheeps cloathing, which went forth from the Apoſtles, which all Nations came to drink their cup; and ſo whether or no amongſt you, are not all the names, heads, and horns one puſhing againſt another? and whether or no you are not all wraſtlers againſt fleſh, and blood and creatures, you are ſtriking them, and beating them, and priſoning them for your bellies, yea to death? did ever the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles do as you do? priſon men, hale men before Courts. Seſſion, Aſſizes, priſon them to death for their bellies as you do; are not you here of them which ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own bellies, which the Apoſtle ſaw amongſt the apoſtates; do not you priſon them, and priſon to death for Tythes, ſucceſſors, which coveted no mans ſilver, nor gold, nor apparel, but gave freely; do you walk in the Sheeps ſteps, the Apoſtles ſteps that Chriſt ſaies to, freely ye have received, freely give. Now I ſay, you are the <hi>Popes</hi> ſucceſſors, have not you Tythes as they have? have not you his Houſes with Croſſes on them? do not you obſerve the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56052:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Names that he gave to the Colledges? do not you obſerve the Names that he gave dayes, tell me of whoſe Family are you; there is a ſtop between the Pope and the Apoſtles, and you both; but you and the Pope having had both the ſheeps cloathing, and the Wolf covered with it, and you, and he, and them his Company, are all the wraſtlers againſt fleſh and blood, inſtead of bringing the Creatures into the liberty of the ſons of God, inſtead of deſtroying the power that capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates the Creatures and cauſes the enmity amongſt Creatures, deſtroying the creatures that be contrary minded to you, and ſo that is the Popes ſpirit indeed, and differs not a whit from it, and ſo in that you are his ſucceſſors, but it is not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſpirit, ſo your Miniſtry, and ſpirit and the Popes, is quite another than the Apoſtles, who warſtled not againſt fleſh and blood, but againſt the powers, and ſpiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſo here is your ſpirits and the Popes tryed, and found to be in the Apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 13. And how would you have done to have kept your Sermons in your memory, had not the Bible been turned into Chapters and Verſes 450 years ago, and was it not the Pope and ſuch as belonged to him, that turned it into Chapters and Verſes, and ſo have not you and the Pope been upon one border, having had the Sheeps cloathing; but neither you nor he can endure to hear talk of the light within men, the annointing within men to teach them, Chriſt within them, the Spirit within to lead them, the Word within to be obeyed, that which may be known of God made manifeſt in them, to come to, before they retain God in their knowledge, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Covenant; now this with you is called <hi>non ſenſe</hi> and <hi>whymſies,</hi> which was the pure Doctrine of the Apoſtles, before your and the Popes apoſtacy, with which pure Doctrine you and the Pope are fathomed and comprehended, to which pure Doctrine people are now come, and what you ravened from, and what you went from (to that which they and you) and ravened from, who are burſt into Names, and Sects, and Heaps, wanting the inſide, the life amongſt you, having the outſide the ſheeps cloathing, wraſtling againſt fleſh and blood, deſtroying one another about your Worſhip, Teaching, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry maintenance, yea, as I ſaid before, priſoning to death
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56052:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>for your Bellies; Now may not all ſee whether you be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ravening Wolves, ſo have ravened from the Spirit, the Pope and you in which is the Unity, which the Scriptures were given forth from, which is the bond of peace, which the Apoſtles were in, ſo to that which you and the Pope went from, is people now coming, and come, with the ſame they ſee you, comprehend you, and fathom you; where the Apoſtates and Pope, and you left, is now people come, and to that muſt come, if they come into Unity, if they come to be ſucceeders of the Apoſtles; Glory to the Lord for ever, the Way is found, the Key is found, but not in the Popes hand, nor yours, as the manifeſtation is ſhewed to the whole world, preached on the houſe top, by priſons, by inquiſitions, yea, by priſoning to death for your Bellies, and priſoning for your Bellies, and ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people up and down, from Sizes, to Seſſions, and Courts, for your Bellies, and deſtroying one another about the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt's, and the Apoſtles words, and burſt into Names, Heaps, Sects, Heads, about them, ſo this doth ſhew, That neither you nor the Pope, nor any of his adherers, nor Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates ſince the Apoſtles, have had the Key, but the Key has been taken away from people by them that went from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, which in wardly ravened; but the Key is found, your firſt going out is opened, and the Apoſtates and apoſtacy ſeen, and your garments are turned up, and your Wolf is ſeen, and your Grand-father the Pope ſeen, and you have kept the Sheeps cloathing the outſide, and have been fighting with one another about —; ſo the way to break off from Popery is to come to that which the Pope, and his adherents, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates went from, which they ravened from, that went from the Apoſtles, and then deſtroy his image, root out his Name from amongſt you, and his marks, and receive them not, call not your dayes by his naming, and own not him to be your Teacher, the Pope, deny his Doctrine, and deny Heatheniſh practiſes, cuſtoms, deny the Heathen to teach you to call your Months, and your Week-dayes; deny the Pope to teach you to name your Colledges, as St. <hi>Peters,</hi> St. <hi>Johns, Trinities, &amp;c.</hi> and deny the Popes Orders amongſt your Teachers that are made Teachers at your Colledges, if you will be called not the ſucceſſors of the Pope, and will have Popery broken down
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56052:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>amongſt you, and break down your Glaſſes which you have preached and read your Sermons by, by the hour, like Sayers of the Maſſe, and ſo have been the limiters of the holy One, and quenchers of the Spirit, none muſt ſpeak in the time of his Glaſſe, here is popiſh like; and did not the true Apoſtle ſay, <hi>You may all ſpeak One by One?</hi> If any thing be revealed to another that ſits by, let the firſt hold his peace, is not this confuſion amongſt you, and ſets you all in confuſion and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order? Are you the ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles, their Church, and Miniſtry; nay, you are declared to be Apoſtates from them; your Goals, Priſons, declare it: Again, If you will have Popery down, and the ſmell of it out of the Laud, down with your Papiſts houſes with Croſſes on the ends of them, your Steeple-houſe, called Churches, and your Pulpits, and your Tythes, and your Offerings, and your Glesb-lands, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with them, come out of the Earth, and abroad in the Nations, preach the Goſpel without Bag; <hi>Judas</hi> the betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was of the Miniſtry that carried the Bag; the ſucceſſion of the Apoſtles was turned againſt by the Apoſtates, them that in wardly ravened and rent forth from the Apoſtles, and ſo turned againſt them that kept the teſtimony of Jeſus the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Propheſie; who have long ravened up and down, and raigned in the world; but the Saints and the Lamb ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, and the everlaſting Goſpel ſhall be preached to them that dwell upon the Earth, and the holy Prophets ſhall rejoyce over her, which went forth from the Apoſtles, which made War againſt the Saints, that turned againſt the Saints, which the Saints and the Lamb ſhall again overcome, and the everlaſting Goſpel be preached; And is it not ſaid, The blood of the Martyrs, the blood of the Saints, the blood of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which the Whore, the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophets has ſlain, they have drunk, and made themſelves drunk with it; and are not you of them that perſecure to death, that P<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſon to death the Saints, becauſe they cannot give you Tythes; and have not you priſoned to death many, perſecuted to death many in this Nation, ſpilt the bloud of many in this Nation, of the Saints, priſoned to death in <hi>York,</hi> priſoned to death in <hi>Durbam,</hi> priſoned to death in <hi>Norwich,</hi> priſoned to death in <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> priſoned to death in <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> priſoned in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56052:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Appleby</hi> till a little before death, and in <hi>Briſtol</hi> there priſoned till carried out in a Basket, beaten, and bruiſed; and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and will not the bloud of the innocent cover you, | and many in the Nation lyes in priſon; how can you ſay, you are the Apoſtles ſucceſſors, think you the Lord will not avenge himſelf of you, for the bloud of his Saints, for the bloud of his prophets, and many beaten and bruiſed by you in your Steeple-houſes, and not long lived after; and have not more of the Saints been priſoned by you, and for you, in this Nation within theſe four or five years laſt paſt, then was in all Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, and ever ſince by Papiſts and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 14. Where did the Apoſtles, the true Church, ſet ſome dayes apart to eat Fiſh, and not other Fleſh, as many of your people does on the dayes you call <hi>Wedneſdayes,</hi> and <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes,</hi> and to obſerve <hi>Cbriſtmaſs, Eaſter, Whitſontide,</hi> calling them <hi>Feaſtival times,</hi> and making abundance of proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deſtroying the Creatures, uſing Gaming, Dancing, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſing themſelves, and play dayes; when and where by Cards, Dice, Shovel board, Drinking, much filthineſſe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and abominable practiſes; where did the Apoſtles or Saints any ſuch things, pract ſe, or obſerve <hi>Shrove-tueſday, Good-friday, Albollow day;</hi> is not the Pope the Father of all ſuch as obſerve theſe; they follow his Doctrine, and do not you all hold up his Doctrine, power, and authority, that holds up St. <hi>Michaels day,</hi> St. <hi>Andrews day,</hi> St. <hi>Matthews d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> St. <hi>Marks day,</hi> St. <hi>Maries day, Chaiſtmaſs day, Whitſontide, Eaſter,</hi> your <hi>Feaſt dayes,</hi> and <hi>Faſt</hi> the <hi>Evens</hi> of them, and <hi>Holy Thurſday,</hi> and has not the Pope been your Teacher; where did <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> or any of the Apoſtles ſet up <hi>Stevens day</hi> before their deceaſe, or <hi>Jobn Baptiſts day,</hi> or any of the Saints dayes that were ſlain before their deceaſe, or command that any ſhould obſerve their dayes after them, ſhew it by the Scripiure, or elſe acknowledge you have kept the people in ignorance, and have held up the <hi>Popes</hi> Doctrine, and yet would ſeem to deny him; and yet his foundation is ſtanding, and you have laid no other; now how can you take the Oath of <hi>Abjuration,</hi> and the foundation of Popery yet ſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, and you have built upon it from generation to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56052:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>generation, and have not openly declared againſt it, but kept people in ignorance: and thus has people been kept and nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up in Superſtition and Idolatry by ſuch as you that have ſerved your bellies, and ſpeak againſt the Pope in words, while his foundation is lying amongſt you; this is the worſt of mens conditions, to ſpeak a gainſt men behind their backs, but make uſe of their wiſdom, doctrine, and underſtanding for their ends, for their eaſe; Come ſearch the Scriptures, and ſee if ever there were ſuch things amongſt the Apoſtles, and ſee how far you are from the Apoſtles, and how near of kin to the Pope; do you think that all your works ſhall not be brought to judgement?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queris</hi> 15. And how differ you from the Papiſts, and the Pope, who ſay the Spirit is in the Sacrament as you call it; and the Pope ſaith, its his body after conſecration; and what is it that you have your prieſts and Teachers in <hi>England,</hi> which is not from the Pope? and what foundation have you to ſtand upon, but what he has laid in all your practice; as your making Miniſters by Colledges as he did and doth, and your Orders and degrees from him, and ſprinkling Infants from him, and your ſinging <hi>Davids Conditions</hi> in <hi>Meetre</hi> from him, your Tythes and Maintenance from him, and your Churches from him, and your Bells from him; and have not you many old popiſh and heatheniſh books, which your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren read, and are taught in; and do not you ſet a croſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>A. B. C.</hi> calling it Chriſts croſs, and ſo begin to train them up in popery as ſoon as they can ſpeak, train them up with old Popiſh books, and way of Learning, and then ſend them to the papiſts Colledge till they be fit to go to the popiſh-houſe to get theirliving; are not your daies named by the <hi>Pope,</hi> and your obſerving of times from the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the names of your Colledges from the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the names of your Steeple-houſes from him, and the names of your week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies and months left to you by the <hi>Pope,</hi> your praying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after Sermon left to you by <hi>Pope,</hi> and your preaching by hour-glaſſes, and your taking Texts, and your <hi>Clerks</hi> to ſay, <hi>Amen,</hi> and your Ringing ſo many times; and the ſetting of your Steeple-houſes eaſt and weſt, and your churching of Women from him, and your Marrying, and your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56052:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſerving ſo long at Colledges before you be made Miniſters from the <hi>Pope,</hi> your wearing long Robes, and black cloaths, and your being called of men Maſter, ſeeing Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Be not ye called of men Maſter,</hi> and your Pulpit ſet in the higheſt place of the Aſſemblies from the Pope; and was not he him that laid this foundation for you, upon which you ſtand? and how can you take the Oath of Abjuration when your heads are covered with Popery? the Cioſs ſtands over your houſes, over your heads; was not your Steeple-houſes from the Pope; and your ſweating from the Pope, ſeeing Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> is not all your burying your people in that which hath been called hallowed ground from the Pope? and your praying with two caps on your heads, and preaching, and yet ſaying, if a man have a hat on, he is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Is not your Tythes, Eaſter-reckonings, Midſummer-dues, Oblations, Obventions, Mortuaries, all from the pope, and did not he lay this foundation? and have not you built on it? and are not you building on it yet? and was this the foundation of the Apoſtles, or the Saints before their deceaſe, or the apoſtates from them? who built all your Parſonage-houſes, and gave you all your Gleab-lands, and the Tenths of all mens labours; and who ſet up Firſt-fruits, and Tenths, but the Pope, ſince the dayes of the apoſtacy from the Apoſtles? did not he claim them as his wages; and if you have denied the Pope and his work, why do you ſtill pay his wages, and take it? how many hundred thouſand pounds a year is gotten in this Nation by you that make a trade of the Scriptures, whoſe foundation in ſo doing was never from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, nor thoſe that gave forth the Scriptures, but from the pope, and thoſe that are apoſtated from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. Now are not the hidden things of popery brought to light, and ripped up as the hidden things of <hi>Eſau</hi> was in the time of old; now are not the Hypocrites ſeen, that cry againſt the Pope in words, and ſtands upon their foundation which is laid; was not the Pope the beginner of your Organs, and all manner of Muſick ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, had the Apoſtles and Saints O<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gans amongſt them, and ſo many ſorts of Muſick before their Deceaſe; yea but if you do ſay, we have laid aſide Surplus, and we have laid aſide Tippet and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56052:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Rails, and Altar, and ſigning Children with the Croſs, and God fathers, and Marrving with the Ring, and we have laid away our Organs in many places and the Croſſes that were upon our Steeple-houſes, and in the Yards and high-waies are pulled down, and ſome of our May-poles are thrown down, and ſome of us do not obſerve Lent, nor eat Fiſh on <hi>Fridaies,</hi> nor read the Common-prayer-book taken out of the Maſs, nor read over the dead body at Buryings, oh deceit; who plucked down theſe th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs? how cryed you againſt theſe things, before the Sword of the Magiſtrate and the Souldiers broke your Pictures our of your windows, and threw ſome of your Croſſes down, and the reſt ſtands, and its ſaid they do no hurt; when do you go up and trample down popery, and throw the Croſs off your Steeple-houſe, and you ſay they that are in the high-way are for marks; oh deceit! why cannot you ſet up poſts if you will have marks; and had the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate but been faithful when he was beginning to throw down your Croſs, he would have let never a one ſtood in <hi>England,</hi> and have hurled them down in other Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 16. You Magiſtrates, when gave you the Prieſts the Oath of Abjuration to renounce Popery? or when took they it that has the Popiſh Houſe with the Popiſh Croſs on the end of it wh<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch they preach in, and Papiſh pictures in the windows, and Bells to call them together,<seg rend="decorInit">&amp;</seg> Popiſh names to their Houſes, as <hi>St. Maries, St. Johns, St. Peters, St Pauls,</hi> and calls their Colledges by the names of the Saints which the Papiſts gave them; when did the Prieſts renounce theſe names; when did the Prieſts renounce the Croſſes on the Steeple-houſe-ends; and how is it ſo many of them ſtand on the Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple houſe end yet, and pictures in the windows; and how is it that they call their dayes by the names the Pope gave to them, and Houſes, and Colledges; and when took theſe the Oath of Abjuration, or when was it to them proffe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to renounce Popery; when was the Oath of Abjura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion put to thoſe that have their Tythes, Eaſter-Reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onings, Midſummer-dues, Obventions, Oblation, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries, who was the firſt Layer, the foundation of all this, but the Pope, and how can they renounce him and keep them. Now if you do ſay you have left off Maſs, though the Croſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56052:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtands upon many of your Houſes-ends yet, and your houſes be called by the Popiſh names; and ye have your Eaſter-Reckonings, and Midſummer dues, and your Tythes, and Gleab lands, which was the Popes maintenance that he allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and he laid forth, as having no other, nor can tell how to get any other; how can ye take his wages then, and will not do his work: was not the wages then given to him that did the work, that ſaid the Maſs; when took you the Oath of Abjura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that take this wages; when did the Apoſtle ſet up Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummer-dues, and Tythes, and Temples with Croſſes; are not you ſheltered under this, and covered with popery, when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced you all theſe things, anſwer. And ſeeing that you take the wages that the Pope ſet forth, your Eaſter-reckonings, Tythes, Gleab-Lands, Midſummer dues, that ye hold up the maintenance, and not do the work; would ye not do the work, ſay the Maſs if that it ſhould be put upon you, ſeeing you take the wages that did the work, who dares truſt you; and is it honeſt to take the wages, and not do the work; when did you ever renounce or forſake any of the Popiſh doctrines, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes or ſuperſtitions, but as the Magiſtrate laid them off, and eaſt them off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 17. And where had the Apoſtle a Clerk to say A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and he muſt have his Wages, and if the People would not give it, then he ſued them and ſtrained their goods, as your Clerks do, who take the goods of ſuch as be not of the Church nor of the Congregation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 18. Where did ever the Apoſtles Sue any for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or hale any before Courts for Money, that was not of their Church, or any that was of their Church? Where did ever the Apoſtles put any in priſon for Money, for Tythes, that was not of their Church, or that was of their Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 19. When the firſt Prieſthood fell, did not the Tyths fall with it, and the Maintenance that belonged to it, when the everlasting Prieſthood came in, and the everlaſting Goſpel, they that preached it, lived of it; did the Apoſtles tell the Jews, hat though their Prieſthood was changed, the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance was ſtill to continue, or did they take or require it of them? So when the popes work fals, muſt not his Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ce fall that he gave for doing his work, and is it honeſt for any to take the one that will not do the other?</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56052:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Querie</hi> 20. You that ſay you are Miniſters of Chriſt, and watch for the ſoul, what is the ſoul that you watch for, and what is Conſcience?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 21. You that ſay Propheſie is ceaſed, does not <hi>John</hi> bid the holy Prophets rejoyce over the Beaſt and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Mother of Harlots; how differ you here from <hi>John,</hi> he bids them rejoyce, and you ſay they are ceaſed; do not you here ſhew your Apoſtacy from <hi>Johns</hi> Doctrine: and the Scripture ſaith, the <hi>ſecress of the Lord are revealed to them that fear him,</hi> and you ſay that Revealation is ceaſed; Now had you ſaid, that men had been ceaſed from fearing the Lord, then you might have ſaid, Revealation had been ceaſed better; but upon ſuch the wrath is revealed, and the righteous judgment of God will be revealed, and then you ſhall know that reveala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not ceaſed, and that the Lord does reveal his ſecrets to them that fears him, and upon them that holds his truth in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, and fears not God, he will reveal his righteous judgments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Querie</hi> 22. What are you but like a company of Readers of Maſs, or Readers of Common-prayers, who have many of you gotten your Sermons written in papers, and the old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Expoſitions of Scripture, and ſome of you can carry them a little longer in your memory, it may be as long as an Hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs will run; and how can you be called any other but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Authors, when you will ſay you never heard the voice of God, nor have the ſame ſpi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it as they had who gave forth the Scriptures, as you do publiſh to all the Nation; now here you may all ſee, what a garment you wear and have worn; Now be not angry becauſe we would have you to put off your garments, which the Pope made for you, and to put on the garments of Chriſt, which the Apoſtles and Saints wore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the apoſtaty, which thouſands are now come to, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, glory to the Lord God forever, whoſe dominion is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all dominions, and Kingdom over all Kingdoms, whoſe Scepter is holden forth to all Nations, and his pearle is found amongſt his People, with whom is his right hand.</p>
            <p>You give forth your oath of Abjuration to deny Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation in the Sacrament, and images, and the Pope and his power, to them that are ſnum; me to that which was before
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56052:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Pope came up, which the Apoſtles were in, and deny the Pope and his Sacraments, and his Bread and Wine, and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, and his Images, and his Tythes, and his Pulpit, and his Croſſes, &amp; his Names, &amp; his Purgatory, &amp; his names to his Steeple-houſes, to his Colledges, &amp; to his dayes, and his <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>-reckonings, and <hi>Midſummer</hi> dues, and his Clerk and his Wages, &amp; his Gleab-lands, and his Worſhiping of Names and Images, and dropping of Beads, and his Steeple-houſes and Croſſes on the ends of them, and his Colledges he makes Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters by, and do witneſs Chriſt the ſubſtance, and God who makes Miniſters by Will, and to ſuch you are tendring your oath of Abjuration, that cannot ſwear, but abide in Chriſts Commands, and are come to that which was before the apoſtacy, ſo to ſuch as you know cannot ſwear, that be in the Covenant of God Chriſt Jeſus, in which they have peace with God, and witneſſes the ſubſtance of all Types, Figures, Shadows, Similitudes, and ſee where there is no changing nor ſhadow; and to ſuch you are giving your oath of Abjuration, to deny your Tranſubſtantiation in the Sacrament; who deny all your Sacraments, and all that practiſe them, the Pope and his followers, for the Pope ye know, and the Jeſuits and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts will ſwear for their own ends, but we deny all Religions upon earth that ſtands in ſwearing, and do not own them, but ſee them ſtanding in the apoſtacy, and do witneſs the Religion that is out to of Oaths. Now if you ſay, <hi>Abraham</hi> ſwore, and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſwore, and the Prophets &amp; Prieſts ſwore; Chriſt before <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was, a greater than <hi>Solomon &amp; David</hi> called him Lord; the end of Prieſts &amp; Prophets ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> who reigns over the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph.</hi> And do you not ſay men in ſtrife ſwear, they that are in ſtrife are out of the doctrine of Chriſt; and if you ſay the Angels ſwore, the Angels muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>My Brethren, above all ſwear not, neither by Heaven, nor by earth, nor by any other Oath;</hi> and who does, are in the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</p>
            <p>Have not all theſe things been ſet up ſince the Apoſtles that be amongſt you, and the Papiſts, that deny the Light that hath enlightned every one that comes into the world, by which the world was made: natural lights, made lights, created lights,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56052:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>were made by him that came a light into the World, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens every one that comes into the world, that all men through him might believe, and he that believes not, the light is his condemation, and he is condemned already, <hi>For this is the condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather than light, becauſe their deads be evill;</hi> with which light we ſee before the apoſtacy was, before Pope was, and all that are ſprung from him, the many heads, and names, and horns, which light fathoms and comprehends them all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Pope and his Poſterity are we come to that which he and his Poſterity went from, with which we reign over the world, which will make him, and all his Poſterity, and all the Heathen upon the earth to tremble, who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> QUAKERS.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56052:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Here is ſcarcely any thing to be looked upon in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the Pope is the Author of it; for I have looked upon your Steeple-houſes, and there beheld abundance of Munkiſh faces, pictures, and images, and a Croſſe on the top of the Steeple-houſes, and the Popes Croſſe is upon your half Crowns, ſix pences, and ſhillings, and upon your Gold and ſilver: but Oh ſaith the Profeſſors and Prieſts, we have no popery amongſt us, and we cannot endure the Popes image, and yet ſtamps it upon your ſilver, and upon your Gold, and look upon your Weights and Meaſures, which is not tollerated until the popes image, the Croſſe, be ſtamped upon them; you muſt not Buy nor Sell until the Popes image be upon your Weights, upon your Meaſures; and are not you aſhamed to pluck down Croſſes in ſome places, and yet carry them up and down in your Pockets, and purſes, the Popes image, the Croſſe, and is not the Croſſe the Arms of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and is not the Popes image, the Croſſe, a top of your Stepple-houſes, which you call your Churches, and ſo the Popes image you have ſet up a top of your Church, is not the Croſſe ſtill ſtanding, and upon your Ships, is not the Croſſe upon your ſilver, upon your Gold, upon your Weights and Meaſures; and was not the Author of all theſe Croſſes the Pope, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, who ſaid <hi>the Croſſe of Chriſt is the power of God,</hi> and is not the power of God, the arm of the Lord, by which he doth mighty acts to Rule Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions withal? And is not the Arms of <hi>Scotland</hi> called Saint <hi>Andrews Croſſe,</hi> and is not the Seal of <hi>Ireland</hi> the Harp and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56052:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Croſſe, the Arms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> the Croſſe, and your Buying and Selling Weights and Meaſures is by the Croſs, and Steeple houſes, and ſhips with the Croſſe on the top of them, a top of your Gold and ſilver, the Popes Croſſe is; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon your Bibles, both new and old Tranſlations, there you may find the Popes image, the Croſſe, almoſt upon every thing? Is not the Croſſe a top of the <hi>Mace</hi> that is carried to the Parliament Houſe, and is not the croſſe pictured in the Parliament Houſe, and how many of them called Knights, Lords, and Gentlement that bears their Croſſes in that which, you call your Sheilds, or Arms, or Eſcutcheon, and fight for it, and kill one another for it, and ſpend many thouſand pounds for it; and is not the Pope the Supream Author, the firſt beginner of them ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, of all theſe Croſſes; and upon almoſt all your ſignes in the City the Croſſe is ſet up, in Taverns, Inns, and Alehouſes, and other bad Houſes hath their Croſſe upon their ſigns, and many Water-men wears the Popes Croſſes upon their Breaſts, which is neer unto their hearts; and the Pope is glad of theſe things, that bis Croſſes ſhould be ſo much affected and ſet up for the Arms <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Croſſes almoſt in every place, and is not the Popes Croſſe upon the Arms of <hi>London,</hi> your chief City; is not the Croſſe upon the very City <hi>Mace,</hi> and is not the Popes Croſſe upon your Ships, and upon your Gold, and Silver, Weights and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, ye ſet the Popes Croſſes upon your ſigns, upon your ſelves, upon your Eſcutcheons, ye ſet the Popes Croſſe upon your Crowns, upon your Coaches, upon your Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Badges you may find the Popes image, the croſſe; and doth not the Porters carry the croſſe hanging about their Girdles; and do not your Carmen carry the croſſe in a little piece of Wood up and down the City in a Cart, the Popes red Croſſe rides up and down in the Cart; and is not all your Swords, Knives, Cannons, and inſtruments of War ſtampt with the Popes croſſe, all that are made in this City: And you ſet the Popes croſſe upon the Broad Seal of <hi>England,</hi> and was not the Pope ſupream Author of all theſe croſſes: And how long is it ſince you left ſprinkling your Children with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56052:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſign of the Croſſe, and was not the Popes croſſe the firſt thing your Children uſe to learn in their Horn books, and look upon the chief place of your City, the <hi>Exchange,</hi> there you may find upon the pictures of your Kings, and of your Queens, the Popers croſſe; and is not this a ſign you have loſt the croſſe of Chriſt, the power of God, that you ſet the Popes croſſe upon all theſe things that be in eſteem, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to your Dominions? And is not this a ſign that you have loſt the croſſe of Chriſt, which is the power of God, and all theſe croſſes without (as Wood, Stone, Iron, Gold, Silver, Braſſe, Tinn, Lead, Glaſſe) carving and painting the Popes image; the croſſes hath all been ſet up ſince the dayes of the Apoſles, in the apoſtacy, which the Pope hath been the firſt Author of them, in the night of darkneſſe, and your Hirelings, and Teachers, are eſtabliſhed by the Broad Seal, in which is the croſſe, and that gives them an entrance into their Miniſtry, and Function; with the Popes croſſes, is their Commiſſion ſealed, with their Fathers croſſe, who is the Author of it, by which right they creep into their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Maſle-houſes, with the croſſe on the end of them, who have loſt the Seal of the Spirit, and yet they call the <hi>Quakers</hi> popiſh, which all theſe things came up ſince the dayes of the Apoſtkes, and ſince men have Witneſſed their Salvation wrought out with fear and trembling, and have loſt the Croſſe, the power of the Spirit of God; in which Croſſe of Chriſt, the power of God, the Apoſtles were in, before the Pope and his croſſe came up, is the <hi>Quakers</hi> come into, and denies all his ſupremacy and croſſes, in what nature ſoever they are found in, are they denied, and witneſes only the power of God to be the croſſe of Chriſt, and denies all other ſtamps with croſſes; and it is a ſhame to all Religions Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and Magiſtrates, to have the dirty Popes croſſe upon all theſe things afore-mentioned; and upon the Conduits and Standards ſtands the Popes croſſe, and upon <hi>London Bridge</hi> are many of the Popes croſſes ſet up; and the bounds of your Lands and pariſhes are the Popes to be found, where the Prieſt once a year uſed to go a Proceſſioning, cleanſing thoſe croſſes, and then ſtrewing them with Flowers.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56052:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>now if we own the Popes Authority which is called ſupream, we ſhould own his croſſes; but we that are come to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, deny the Popes croſſe, and witneſſe the power of God, the croſſe of Cheiſt, ſo root out all the Poper croſſes out of the Land and Nations, and let not the Popes croſſe ſtand amongſt you; and come to the power of God, the croſſe of Chriſt, that you may have another wiſdom beyond the Popes to order things withal, and throw out his works, for the croſſe was the Popes work, for that was ſet up by his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and few of them yet plucked down, and ye have an underſtanding, to give ſignfications to things, that we may know them by, without the croſſe, for the Pope is glad as long as you keep his croſſes upon your Seals, upon your Maces, upon your Gates of your City, upon your Steeple-houſes end, upon moſt part of your Signes, Ships, Badges, Conduits, Bibles, Flags, Colours; the Pope is glad as long as you have his image, the croſſe, ſet upon all theſe things, which have had a great authority; therefore ſweep it out of the Land with the power of God, which is the croſſe of Chriſt, that is the word of the Lord unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the Seed of</hi> GOD, <hi>called</hi> Quakers.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:56052:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>HEre all may ſee how they have been out of the power of God, which the Apoſtles were in, which power is the Croſs of Chriſt, <hi>1 Cor. 1.18.</hi> and how ſince people have been Apoſtated from it.</p>
            <p>And how the Pope hath ſpread his Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and ſet up his Croſſe, which the Apoſtates from the power of <hi>God</hi> was the firſt Author of them, who apoſtated from the power of the Croſs of Chriſt, apoſtated from <hi>God,</hi> and ſet up wooden Croſſes, and ſtone Croſſes, juſt like the Heathen when they went from the life of <hi>God,</hi> they ſet up Images; but now with the power of <hi>God</hi> the Croſs of Chriſt, are all theſe Apoſtates ſeen, and the ſetters up of thoſe wooden croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſtone croſſes, the founder of them is found out, and with the power of the Lord muſt be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded which went forth from the power of <hi>God</hi> in the dark, and by the uſurped authority upon moſt of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56052:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>things ſet up and ſtamped, their outward carnal croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and carnal images, and ſo out of the image of <hi>God,</hi> the power of <hi>God,</hi> the croſs of Chriſt, with it you muſt be all confounded, both croſſes, image, and founder of them, but the life and power of <hi>God</hi> is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen which the Apostles were in before the apoſtates, which the people called Quakers are come into that.</p>
            <p>And here is likewiſe ſome Queries for all Profeſſors and Teachers, that they may give an account of them, for people in general would be ſatisfied: therefore it doth concern Teachers and Prieſts to anſwer, and give a publick account of them to the people, that all may ſee from what ſtock and root they come.</p>
            <p>For theſe things the people have long ſtumbled at, and look that the Prieſt ſhould give ſatisfaction concerning theſe things, which if no anſwer, the people may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them apoſtates from the Apoſtles, which ſees the day moſt of theſe things have got up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From a Lover of truth, and Righteouſneſs, and Peace, that it may be eſtabliſhes upon the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
